字幕制作：冰龙
冰冰高清www.aapig.com.cn
欢迎高清爱好者加入论坛，共享清晰世界
黑暗中，听得到女人的哭泣
婴儿的嚎啕
男人的呐喊
有人祈求获救
有人祈求速死
但更多人以为诸神已离弃
天地万物落入永恒的黑暗
公元79年，小普林尼目击纪录
片名：庞贝
北不列颠尼亚，公元62年
凯尔特马族的反叛
总督要重开这些贸易路线
The Governor wants these
trade routes re-opened.
叛乱的凯尔特人必须根除
These rebel Celts need to be
dealt with once and for all.
这旨令要明确传达到各领地
This entire territory
requires a clear
and well-defined message.
是，科佛斯司令
Yes, Tribune Corvus.
No!
杀掉他们
Kill them.
格杀勿论
Kill them all.
Ah!
伦丁尼姆(伦敦旧称)
不列颠尼亚都城
17年后
Useless!
你把我从温柔乡拖来看这个？
You've dragged me from a perfectly
adequate brothel for this?
我想不通凯撒为何属意这种狗窝
What Caesar saw in this
hell hole, I'll never know.
养这些色雷斯人不便宜
These Thracians are far
too costly to feed.
他们老是把警卫搞成残废
They're always maiming the guards.
我在寻找新奇事物，贝雷特
I'm looking for something new,
Bellator, something fresh.
才有新鲜感
大家唤他凯尔特
They call him The Celt.
他的族人都是驯马高手
They say his people were horsemen
他是唯一幸存者
and that he is the last of them.
Celt! Celt! Celt!
凯尔特...！
这人留在乡下浪费了吧，主人？
Wasted out here in the provinces,
wouldn't you say, Master?
"不列颠尼亚，伦丁尼姆"
"庞贝城"
让路！快让路！
Make way! Make way!
离开道路，闪开
Off! Off the road! Off!
离开道路
Off the road!
让路给上等人
Make way for your betters!
快走，人渣
Move it, scum!
离开道路
Clear the way there!
快走
Move!
那匹马
The horse.
回去队伍，奴隶
Back in line, slave!
那匹马很痛苦，蠢蛋
The horse is in pain,
you ignorant pig!
住手
Stop!
让他帮那匹马
Let him help the horse.
是，小姐
Yes, My Lady.
放松，放松，乖
Easy. Easy, boy.
压住前腿上方
Put pressure on the
top of the leg here,
这样它断气时才不会痛苦
so he doesn't feel the
pain when I move him.
抱歉，小姐，他是野蛮人
I'm sorry, My Lady. He's a savage.
起来
Get up!
换一匹马
Harness another horse.
为何那个粗人要杀马？
Why would the brute do that?
因为那是最仁慈的做法
Because it was the
kindest thing to do.
走吧
Come.
谢谢
Thank you.
快走
Go on!
在罗马看那么多男人...
A whole year in Rome and I
never saw you look at any man
你从未有看那奴隶的眼神
the way you looked at that slave.
我不敢相信他的力量
I can't believe he had
the strength to do that.
你没看见他的肌肉吗？
Didn't you see his muscles?
我不是那个意思
That's not what I meant.
真的？
Really?
别逗我了
Oh, please...
你看，就在那里
Look. There it is.
我们到家了
We're home.
庞贝城
维纳丽亚节
车夫，怎么了？
Driver, what is it?
维纳丽亚节，小姐
The Vinalia, My Lady.
封街，到处是醉汉
The streets are blocked.
Drunkards everywhere.
干嘛？
- What?
- Come on.
走吧
小姐？
My Lady?
小姐
My Lady!
回别墅见
We'll meet you back at the villa.
小姐
My Lady!
我记得每座雕像，每个街角
I remember every statue,
every street corner.
会使你想念罗马吗？
Does it make you miss Rome?
会使我忘记那里
It makes me forget it.
凯西雅，真高兴见到你
Cassia, oh, it's so
good to see you.
但你怎么回来了？
But how are you here? We weren't
expecting you until after Vinalia.
我们以为节庆后你才会回来
我受不了在罗马多待一天
I couldn't bear to spend
another day in Rome.
太多自大男巴着我奉承
Too many arrogant men who
flatter you with their presence.
听起来我的宝贝长大了
It sounds like my baby
is no longer a child.
爸，你在哭吗？
- Father, are you crying?
- Shh.
别说出去，否则我做生意会被坑
Tell no one.
Or I'll never haggle a
decent price again.
我们好想你
We missed you.
不得了，这全是你的行李？
Juno's tit! Is this
all your luggage?
你是买下整座罗马城吗？
What have you done, purchase
the entire city of Rome?
有遇到心上人吗？
Did you meet anyone there?
回到庞贝城没人值得一提
Nobody worth talking
about in Pompeii.
别担心
Well, not to worry.
你爸以昭告全市的单身汉你回来了
I think your father has informed
every unmarried man in
the city of your return.
不会吧，真的？
Oh, no. Really?
快来，我要听罗马的每件事
Now, come on. I want to
hear everything about Rome.
我好想你
I've missed you.
欢迎到你们的新家，野蛮人
Welcome to your new home, savages.
继续走
Keep walking!
站住
Stop!
解开他们
Unlock them.
喂这些畜牲
Feed these animals.
小飞
Vires!
我好想你
Oh, I missed you.
我好想你，你好
I missed you. Hello.
它很高兴见到你，小姐
He's pleased to see you, My Lady.
我看得出它受到良好照顾
And I can see he's
been in good hands.
谢谢你，菲力
Thank you, Felix.
明天一早我会把小飞准备好给您
And I'll have Vires ready for
you first thing tomorrow.
今晚我会亲自训练他
I'll exercise him myself tonight.
谢谢你
Thank you.
明天见
I'll see you tomorrow.
阿提卡斯
Atticus...
那应该是凯尔特
I think that's The Celt.
哪个凯尔特？
Which Celt?
独一无二的凯尔特
The Celt.
听说他比你还快
They say that Celt is
faster even than you.
听说不足为据
They always say that.
他要你报上名字，凯尔特
He wants to know your name, Celt.
报上名字，你杀了他兄弟
He wants the name of the
man who killed his brother.
他要我报上名字？
He wants to know my name?
两杯酒押色雷斯大汉
Two wine rations on
the big Thracian.
两杯酒，成交
Two wine rations. Done.
给我解释
Explain.
不是他起头的，他正在用餐
He did not start it.
He was trying to eat.
贝雷特
Bellator!
你得职责是看好这些人，不是吗？
Your purpose is to care
for these men, is it not?
要是没人付钱观赏
别平白让他们自相残杀
Having them bite pieces
from one another
is of no value if no one
is paying to see it.
抱歉，葛雷克斯主人
I'm sorry, Master Graecus.
那个没用了
That one is done.
这个还有救
This one...
Can be repaired.
再有下次，你要付出代价
And the next time, Bellator,
it will be at your cost.
我会记住你，凯尔特
I'll remember you, Celt.
开门
Open the gate!
关上
Close it!
你欠我两杯酒，凯尔特
You owe me two wine rations, Celt.
渴了，好
Thirsty? Okay.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
小飞！
Vires!
醒来，人渣
Wake up, scum.
站起来
On your feet.
别紧张
Relax.
要是我想杀你
If I was going to kill you, Celt...
我早就下手了
I would have done it already.
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
我们迟早要交谈的
We will have to speak
at some point.
没必要
No, we don't.
我们只是迟早要杀掉对方
What we have to do is kill
each other at some point.
所以别管我的名字
So my name's my own, I have
no interest in learning yours.
我也没兴趣打听你的名字
所有人出来
Everyone out!
快走
Move!
你老了，阿提卡斯
You're getting old, Atticus.
许多新血等不及要取代冠军
Plenty of young flesh out here just
aching to take apart a champion.
明天我在竞技场再获胜
When I win in the arena
tomorrow, I'm a free man.
我就自由了
罗马法律
It's Roman law.
你无可奈何
And there's nothing
you can do about it.
阿提卡斯，我的冠军
Atticus, my champion,
明天你有幸终结比赛
tomorrow you have the honor
of closing the games.
但首先
First,
我来替你找个旗鼓相当的对手
let us see if I have
found an opponent
worthy of you.
哪个可怜虫该为我的自由而死？
Now...
Who's the poor bastard who
has to die for my freedom?
很不幸，凯尔特
Unlucky, Celt.
太不幸了
Very unlucky.
但我不会出手太重
But I'm going to
take it easy on you.
给你机会明天试身手
Give you a fighting
chance for tomorrow.
你小有名气
You may have earned
your reputation,
但没遇过我这种强敌吧
but not fighting against
a gladiator like me.
看起来你输定了
You made that a little too obvious.
我看起来输定了吗？
Did I make that too obvious?
贝雷特！
Bellator!
让开
Get away!
别挡路
Get out of the way! Get up, scum!
起来，人渣
回去干活
Back to work!
你为什么救我一命？
Why did you save my life?
斗士不该死于背后一刀
No gladiator should die
from a blade to the back.
要死也要死于正面攻击
When you die, the blow
will come from the front.
我保证明天就是你死期
I promise it will be tomorrow.
我会亲手证明
And it will come from my hand.
我能给你更好的保证
Well, I can make you
a better promise.
到时，你会死得很快
When the time comes,
your death will be quick.
我会亲手证明
And it will come from my hand.
别担心，你的计划完美无瑕
Don't worry. Your plan is
nothing short of brilliance.
只有疯子才会劝阻皇帝投资
Only a mad man would advise the
Emperor against investing.
但愿皇帝不会派来疯子
Well, let us hope that the
Emperor has not sent us one.
Keep up in time.
议员，原谅我们无法去港口接您
Senator,
do forgive us for not being able
to receive you at the harbor.
赛佛勒斯
Severus, you're a busy man.
I understand entirely.
你是大忙人，我完全谅解
再说如果我有像你这种娇妻
Besides, if I had a wife
as beautiful as yours,
我一定不急着离开她身边
I'd be in no hurry to
forsake her company.
我是昆塔亚兹科佛斯议员
I am Senator Quintas Attius Corvus.
愿神明容我为你们的款待祈福
May the gods grace me to
bless your kind hospitality.
您太客气了，议员
You're most welcome, Senator.
议员，告诉我们罗马的消息
So, Senator, tell us
the news from Rome.
新皇帝提图斯即位顺利吗？
How does the new
emperor, Titus, fare?
"新"皇帝？
The "new" emperor?
新皇帝提图斯很顺利
The new emperor, Titus, fares well.
他父亲维斯帕先受到人民爱戴
His father, Vespasian,
was loved by his people,
他们会爱屋及乌
and they continue that
love for his son.
正如神旨
- As the gods demand?
- Indeed.
确实
赛佛勒斯，我想向你请教
Severus, I have a question for you.
我从港口到这里
On my journey from the harbor,
我注意到有些镇民背对着我
I noticed some of your townsfolk
turned their backs towards me.
那不会造成问题吧？
There wouldn't be some kind
of problem, would there?
当地人怨恨罗马？
Some local resentment against Rome?
不，不成问题
No. Nothing of the sort.
只有少数弱势反对我们的计划
A tiny...
A miniscule minority of
opposition to our plans.
但新建设会向人民证明有新的沟渠
But our new construction
will provide the people
with a new aqueduct,
更好的卫生，更大的浴场
better sanitation, bigger
bath houses, a new arena.
新的竞技场
崭新的庞贝城
A whole new Pompeii.
讲新皇帝不恰当吗？
What was all that about
the new emperor?
他是政客，留意你的发言
He's a politician.
Be careful what you say to him.
你想我们能跟他做生意吗？
Do you think we can
do business with him?
如果皇帝没兴趣，他就不会来了
He wouldn't be here if the
Emperor wasn't interested.
爸为什么邀请罗马议员来家里？
Why would father invite a
Roman senator into our home?
你怎么能容忍这种事？
How could you allow such a thing?
想要罗马富豪来投资
If we want Rome's rich to
spend their money here,
就得依照他们的要求
we must keep up with
what they demand.
他们的要求？
What they demand?
爸不知道罗马的现况吗？
Does father have any idea what's
going on in Rome right now?
自从提图斯掌权，一切都走样了
Since Titus took power,
everything has changed.
皇帝只听小人的话
Every crooked man now has
the ear of the Emperor.
他们自认能为所欲为
And they assume that they can
take whatever they want.
凯西雅，你为什么提早回家？
Cassia, why did you
come home early?
罗马发生什么事？
What happened in Rome?
我只是受够了
I'd simply had my fill of it.
母亲，那是小飞吗？
Mother, is that Vires?
冷静，冷静
Whoa. Whoa. Easy! Easy!
小飞，你来这里干嘛？
Vires, what are you doing out here?
菲力在哪里？
Where's Felix?
我听说明天是你的最后一战
I heard tomorrow
is your last fight.
没错
That's right.
杀了你之后，他们就会给我自由
After I kill you, they
will give me my freedom.
别作梦了
They won't do it.
你这么强，不会放你
Not while your arm's still strong.
自由是罗马的承诺
Freedom is Rome's promise.
你相信他们会履行承诺？
You trust them to
keep that promise?
我相信他们的法律
I trust their law.
斗士只有一种自由
There's only one freedom
for a gladiator.
死在竞技场时不屈不挠
When you die in that arena,
you die unconquered.
当面唾弃罗马
And you spit in the eye of Rome.
那就是你的未来
Then this is your future.
你会以奴隶身分领死
And you die a slave.
我可不同
But not me.
明天罗马会信守承诺
Tomorrow, Rome will make
good on its promise.
可惜你不会活着见证我是对的
You, unfortunately, will not be
alive to see that I am right.
这么有自信？
So sure?
今天我发现你的弱点
Today you showed me
your weaknesses.
你的左臂比右臂没力
Your left arm is weaker
than your right.
所以你为了保护肋骨顾不得脖子
So you protect your ribs at
the expense of your neck.
那你变换重心时该加强攻击力道
And you should learn how to thrust
when you're shifting your weight
也别再偏重上方防卫
and stop favoring a high guard.
那样你就不会那么好猜
It would make you less predictable.
这个
This one.
那个
That one.
Mmm...
还有这两个
These two.
站起来，奴隶们
On your feet, slaves.
好
All right.
你站这里
You, here.
你，野蛮人，站这里
You, barbarian, here!
两个都是一流的斗士
Both excellent fighters.
一个是冠军
One, a champion,
另一个在乡下经过考验和鉴定
and the other, tried and
proven in the provinces.
我要看他的后面
I want to see him from behind.
干嘛这么严肃？
Why so serious?
这种夜班不错嘛
Not so bad for a night's work.
很结实
Firm.
但"武器"持久吗？
But what of his weaponry?
想一窥究竟可得付钱
That is an inspection
you'll have to pay for.
这会是新的竞技场
And this will be the new arena,
特别为战车竞赛设计
specifically designed
for chariot races.
好
Yes.
很详细，赛佛勒斯
Very detailed, Severus.
但我想这个计划不适合帝国投资
But I don't believe
that this project
is really suitable for
an Imperial investment.
皇帝对这种乡间嬉戏没兴趣
These dalliances in the countryside
hold very little interest
for the Emperor.
我听到传闻...
I was led to understand...
不，很遗憾皇帝的未来愿景
No. No. Unfortunately,
the Emperor's vision
是集中在罗马
for the future is
firmly fixed on Rome.
我倒是有兴趣投资
I, however, am
interested in investing.
很好
Good.
把合约拟好
Have the pledges drawn up.
明天比赛后，我就会签字
You'll have my mark on them
tomorrow. After your games.
想必接下来该喝酒了
I do believe a drink is in order.
当然，我们加入宾客好吗？
Of course. Shall we
join our guests?
也许令媛能端出来
Perhaps your daughter can bring it.
小女？
My daughter?
看那里
Look over there.
能跟马说话的奴隶
The slave who can talk to horses.
他真有男人味
He is a fine specimen.
你不能否认
Well, you can't deny it.
转身
Turn around.
凯西雅
Ah, Cassia.
我能占用你一下吗？
May I impose upon you for a moment?
有人要求见你
Your presence has been requested.
当然，父亲
Yes, of course, Father.
拿着，但不是给你的
You will need this.
It is not for you.
凯西雅，容我介绍...
Cassia, may I introduce...
科佛斯议员
Senator Corvus.
凯西雅小姐
Lady Cassia.
天啊，我好想你
My, how I have missed you.
你美极了
You are exquisite.
科佛斯议员，我无言以对
Senator Corvus,
I don't know what to say.
给我的？真体贴
For me? How kind.
你们彼此认识？
You two have met?
赛佛勒斯，你还在啊
Severus, you're still here.
我不知你认识小女
I did not know you
knew my daughter.
那你该听听来龙去脉
Then you should hear
the whole story.
明天在竞技场签约时再聊
Tomorrow in the arena
when I sign your pledges.
谢谢
Thank you.
马克斯
Marcus?
议员和凯西雅在罗马就已相识
The Senator and Cassia
have already met, in Rome.
那她需要监护人
Then she requires a chaperone.
她没有我们都能在罗马熬过一年
She survived a year
in Rome without us.
她一定能在自家露台熬过十分钟
I'm sure she can survive
10 minutes on our balcony.
在罗马我以为我们有共识
In Rome, I thought we
had an understanding.
不，是你个人之见
No. You had an understanding.
我没给你机会
One for which I gave you no cause.
你光是出现就给了我机会，小姐
Your mere presence gives
me cause, My Lady.
像你这种美人
A beauty such as yours has no place
不该待在这种假日胜地
in a holiday resort like this.
当然像你这种尤物
Surely, a creature such as you
只属于永恒之城
can have no home but
in the Eternal City.
议员，我毫无意愿回去罗马
Senator, I have no intention
of returning to Rome.
倘若是以我妻子的身分回去呢？
And if you were to
return as my wife?
你妻子？
Your wife?
你能当作是恭维
You may consider it a compliment.
科佛斯议员，我想你误会我是...
Senator Corvus, I believe
you have mistaken me
在罗马坐你大腿的那种女人
for the kind of woman who drapes
herself across your lap in Rome.
我不愿成为你的妻子
I have no wish to become your wife.
断然拒绝，不出我所料
A spirited refusal.
I would have expected nothing less.
享受维纳丽亚节的尾声吧
Enjoy the remains of the
Vinalia, Senator. Good night.
晚安
这样正常吗？
Is this normal?
是火山，偶尔会有轰隆声
It is the mountain. It
grumbles from time to time.
把这个人带来，我需要他
Bring this man. I need him.
小姐  - 马上
- My Lady
- Now!
小姐，是小飞
My Lady, it's Vires!
拜托，免得它伤了自己
Please, before he injures himself.
我得单独进去
I have to go in alone.
不行
No.
让他进去
Let him.
小姐，他是野蛮人
My Lady, he's a savage.
让他进去
Let him.
冷静
Easy!
小姐，他不可靠
My Lady, he's not safe.
让开
Move.
在外面等
Wait outside.
你怎么做到的？
How did you do that?
我有问他
I asked him.
你在成为斗士前就会骑马？
You could ride before
you were a gladiator?
我在会走路前就会骑马
I could ride before I could walk.
我的族人曾经是驯马高手
My people were horsemen.
"曾经是"？
"Were" horsemen?
族人被罗马人赶尽杀绝
My family were butchered
by the Romans.
很遗憾
- I'm so sorry.
- "Sorry"?
遗憾？
罗马人哪会懂这些
What would a Roman
know of such things?
我不是罗马人，我是庞贝公民
I am not a Roman.
I'm a citizen of Pompeii.
为何到处可见罗马的鹰旗？
Then why do I see Rome's
eagle everywhere I turn?
这跟我无关
I'm no part of that.
在罗马待一年后
After a year in Rome, I hoped
never to see that eagle again.
我再也不想看那面鹰旗了
但那已经渗透到我家门外
And yet, here it is, thrust
into the soil outside my home.
家父相信他能跟那些禽兽协议
My father believes that he can
bargain with those animals.
换作我爸
My father...
会将他们诛尽杀绝
He would have killed
every last one of them.
小姐？
My Lady?
他们逮到你骑在马上会惩罚你
If they catch you up there
they'll punish you.
小姐？
My Lady?
小姐，一切还好吗？
My Lady, is everything all right?
Wait! Come back!
Come back!
怎么了？
What's wrong?
万一他们逮到你跟我在这里
If they catch you
up here with me...
我会说是我自愿
I'll tell them it was my choice.
他们在那里
There they are!
我得送你回去
I have to take you back.
不，你走，留下我
No. You go and leave me here.
你骑走就在机会
If you ride you have a chance.
什么机会？
- A chance at what?
- At freedom.
自由
但你要付出什么代价？
But at what cost to you?
告诉警卫我强行带你来这里
Tell the guards I brought
you here by force.
把责任归咎于我
The blame is mine.
把他拖下马
Get him off that horse!
不是他的错，马逃走，情况失控
It wasn't his fault. The horse
bolted. It was out of control.
议员，拜托，这奴隶救了我一命
Senator, please. This
slave saved my life.
他不该被处决
He does not deserve this.
凯西雅小姐，你没受伤吧？
Lady Cassia, you were unharmed?
我毫发无损
I'm perfectly all right.
要我放这奴隶生路
If I were to spare the
life of this slave,
你要回报我什么？
what would it be worth to you?
议员？
Senator?
想必你明白这个问题，可人儿
I believe you understand
the question, my dear.
我会很感激你的慈悲
I would be grateful for your mercy.
Well...
今天你走运，奴隶
This is your lucky day, slave.
凯西雅小姐救了你的小命
The Lady Cassia has
saved your life.
这奴隶是谁的？
Who owns this slave?
我的，议员
I do, Senator.
那我建议你惩一儆众
Then I suggest you punish
it and then remove it.
15鞭应该足够
Fifteen lashes should suffice.
毕竟慈悲是美德
After all, mercy is a virtue.
父亲，你得制止
Father, you have to stop this.
我爱莫能助
There's nothing I can do about it.
你救了他一命
You saved his life.
你已该庆幸
Content yourself with that.
科佛斯议员有求于你
Senator Corvus requires
a service of you.
我？
Of me?
这个斗士，你明天对他有何安排？
This gladiator.
What do you have planned
for him tomorrow?
他最后上场
He fights last.
跟我的冠军单挑
Single combat against my champion.
不行
No.
他最先上场，也最早送死
He fights first.
And he dies first.
他被鞭15下都没吭一声
Fifteen lashes and he
didn't make a sound.
我原本能阻止发生
I could have prevented this.
我乱了思绪
I don't know what I was thinking.
他让你感到活力
That he made you feel alive?
他让我感到安全
He made me feel safe.
那种男人不应当死在竞技场
A man like that does not
deserve to die in the arena.
这不是你的错，凯西雅
This is not your fault, Cassia.
他激怒议员了
He has caught the Senator's wrath.
我以为离开罗马他会忘记我
I thought that,
in leaving Rome, that man
would forget about me
转而觊觎别的倒霉鬼
and turn his attentions toward
some other poor victim.
今晚我看到他的眼神，阿丽德妮
I saw a look in that man's
eye tonight, Ariadne.
跟我在罗马看到的一样
The same look I saw in Rome.
但议员从未染指你？
But the Senator never
laid a hand on you.
幸好我在他动手前离开罗马
Only because I left
Rome before he could.
现在罗马跟随我们回到庞贝
Now Rome has followed
us back to Pompeii
会搞得天翻地覆
to turn the world inside out.
你真懂得准备比赛
You certainly know how
to prepare for a battle.
希望她值得
I hope she was worth it.
糟蹋了好酒
A terrible waste of good wine.
你有感觉到吗？
Can you feel that?
是诸神
It is the gods.
祂们对芸芸众生自有安排
They have a plan for us all.
也许吧
Perhaps.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
今晚我看到杀死我全家的人
Tonight I saw the man who
killed my whole family.
也许诸神让我存活有其理由
Perhaps the gods spared
me for a reason.
20年前罗马人夺走我的家庭
The Romans took my family
from me 20 years ago.
夜晚我努力回想他们的面孔
At night I try and remember
their faces, but I cannot.
但我想不起来
但我知道总有一天
But I know one day, the gods
will bring me to them again.
神会让我跟他们团聚
我叫米洛
My name is Milo.
阿提卡斯
Atticus.
你，那个隧道
You, that tunnel.
把凯尔特送进那个隧道
Send The Celt into that tunnel.
我以为他要跟阿提卡斯对打
I thought he was to fight Atticus.
你有新的指示
You're being given
new instructions.
是，主人
Yes, Master.
那阿提卡斯呢？
And Atticus?
他照常单挑
He'll fight single
combat as billed.
让他跟斯巴达大汉对打
Put him with the big Spartan.
给观众一场精彩比赛
He'll give the
audience a good show.
那阿提卡斯会打败他赢得自由
And Atticus will beat him
and win his freedom.
观众真的想看到这一幕？
Is that really what the
audience will want to see?
你想说什么？
What are you saying?
不觉得他们宁可看到...
Don't you think they'd rather see
斗士殉身而不是苟活？
a gladiator meeting
death rather than life?
尤其是壮烈牺牲？
Especially a death
as glorious as his?
站住
Stop.
你，那边
You.
That way.
你也是，野蛮人
You too, barbarian.
科佛斯议员
Senator Corvus.
凯西雅小姐
Lady Cassia.
过来坐我身边
Come sit beside me.
用你的智慧给我增光
Give me the benefit of your wisdom.
喜欢看这种竞赛吗？
Do you enjoy the sports?
看人互相残杀为乐，不算竞赛
Men killing each other for our
amusement is not a sport.
到处都是，全是新裂痕
Everywhere. All new.
我没空跟你扯，葛雷克斯
I don't have time for this, Graecus.
What are you suggesting?
你在暗示什么？
取消比赛？
That we cancel the games?
当然不是，只是延后
Of course not.
Merely postpone them.
这座竞技场已矗立一百年
This amphitheater has stood
for a hundred years.
禁得起大地震
It withstood the great earthquake.
可能不安全，睁亮眼
It may not be safe. Use your eyes.
声明在先，我无法负责不堪后果
I'm just saying I cannot
be held responsible
for what may happen.
那就不必，我负全责
Then don't be.
I take full responsibility.
我们哪能期望...
How can we expect Rome to trust
us to rebuild an entire city
罗马托付我们重建整座城市
要是我们办不成简单的格斗赛？
if we can't stage a
simple bloody spectacle?
拿我的行囊来，我要出城几天
Fetch my litter.
I'm leaving town for a few days.
快走！
Move.
站住，铐住他们
Stop. Shackle them!
这是干嘛？
What is this?
这是你最伟大的时刻，阿提卡斯
This is your greatest
moment, Atticus.
你在竞技场的末日
Your final day in the arena.
我应该要单挑的
I'm supposed to fight
single combat.
给他们武器
Bring them their weapons!
祝好运，阿提卡斯
Good fortune, Atticus.
赴死者，我们向你们致敬
To those about to
die, we salute you!
由马克斯卡西赛佛勒主持
By the patronage of
Marcus Cassius Severus
献给提图斯皇帝的盛世
and for the glory of Emperor Titus,
并特此谨记
remember, all here,
the mighty victory
科佛斯议员的非凡胜利
of Senator Quintas Attius Corvus
和他铲平凯尔特人叛乱的功迹
and his annihilation of
the Celtic Rebellion.
凯尔特人叛乱？
The Celtic Rebellion?
您为了帝国的伟大和高贵胜利
Your great and noble victory
for the Empire, Senator,
重开北方贸易路线
re-opening the
northern trade routes.
青史会记下您的壮举
The history books record
it as your finest hour.
我想您应该也想要光荣开赛
I thought perhaps you
might like the honor
of opening these games
in a similar manner.
赛佛勒斯，我受宠若惊了
Severus, you flatter me.
我们会让你享有罗马人的殊荣
We'll make a Roman out of you yet.
庞贝的子民
People of Pompeii!
愿朱比特和维纳斯
May Jupiter and Venus bless the
Vinalia and honor these games!
保佑维纳丽亚节并颂扬比赛
竞赛开始！
Let the games begin!
这不是格斗
- This isn't a battle.
- What?
什么？
这是屠杀
This is a massacre.
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
因为我是过来人
Because I was there.
反叛的凯尔特人正在撤离
The rebel Celts are in retreat,
留下强暴和杀戮尾随而至
leaving rape and
slaughter in their wake,
返回遭亵渎的巢穴
returning to their
unholy lair to feast
饱尝无辜受害者的血肉
on the flesh of their
innocent victims.
这就是你们受训的目的，人渣
This is what you've
trained for, scum.
赶快出来
Now get out there.
昆塔亚兹科佛斯
Quintas Attius Corvus gave them
every chance to surrender.
给予他们投降的每个机会
但慈悲对野蛮人来说是陌生概念
But mercy was an alien
concept to these savages,
怀抱沉重的心
and with heavy heart,
Quintas Attius Corvus
昆塔亚兹科佛斯
下令他的强大军团
ordered his mighty legions, in the
name of the Emperor, to attack.
以皇帝之名攻击！
举盾！
Shields up!
推进！
Push!
你称这是竞赛？
Is this what you call sport?
不，小姐，这不是竞赛
No, Lady Cassia, this is
not sport. This is politics.
这是政治
我们挡不住他们
We can't hold them!
后退
Back!
快跳
赛佛勒斯，我记得不该是这样
Severus, this is not
exactly how I remember it.
那奴隶对你有何意义？
What exactly is that slave to you?
跟你南辕北辙，议员
Everything that you
are not, Senator.
那你该很高兴得知
Then you should be pleased to learn
令尊已把你许配给我
your father has granted
me your hand in marriage.
什么？
- What?
- I made no such arrangement.
我没做过这种约定
因为他知道要是拒绝了
Because he knows
that if he does not,
我会通报提图斯皇帝
I will inform Titus that your
father has called into question
令尊质疑"新"皇帝的能力
our "new" emperor's
ability to rule.
皇帝会把你全家吊死在城墙
Titus will have your entire
family hung from the city walls.
米洛！
Milo!
如果我要嫁给你
If I were to marry you...
凯西雅
- Cassia...
- If I marry you,
如果我嫁给你
我的家人能免于一死吗？
is my family spared?
你的家人就会成为我的家人
Your family will become my family,
受到皇帝的保护
under the protection
of the Emperor.
并拥有各种附带优势
With all of the benefits
that that implies.
庞贝...！
Pompeii! Pompeii! Pompeii!
议员
Senator!
我不会屈服于罗马的力量
I do not yield to
the power of Rome!
我唾弃它
I spit on it!
量他没这个胆
He would not dare.
庞贝...！
Pompeii! Pompeii! Pompeii!
加派士兵进入竞技场
Get a detachment in the arena now.
快去
Now!
你说的对，兄弟
You were right, brother.
他们承诺的一切全是谎言
Everything they promised,
nothing but lies.
赦免！赦免！赦免！赦免！
Live! Live! Live!
你到底想干嘛？
What do you think you're doing?
夫人，坐好
Madame, take your seat!
想活命就给我坐下
If you want to live
you will sit down!
马上
Now!
如果你现在杀他
If you kill him now, on the
tip of 100 Roman arrows,
万箭齐发
他会变成烈士而不是暴民
you make him a martyr to the mob.
你想要那样？
Is that what you want?
把革命带回家给皇帝？
To take home to your
Emperor a revolution?
况且如果你推翻这个决定
And if you reverse this decision,
你在罗马会有何风评？
how will it be spoken of in Rome?
大家会闲言闲语
They will whisper it
behind your back,
说你妻子不顺从你
that you have a wife who
does not obey your will.
你的名声能承受这种污点？
Can your reputation
bear such a weakness?
我可能成为你的妻子
I might become your wife,
but you will never break me.
但你绝对驯服不了我
我会驯服你
But I will break you,
你会温驯到站坐爬都唯我是从
and you will stay broken to
stand, sit or crawl as I decree.
听清楚了吗？
Do you understand me?
普罗克路斯，派人把她带回别墅
Proculus, have your guard
take her back to the villa.
把她关在那里
Keep her there.
我想婚礼应该在罗马举行
I think the wedding
shall be in Rome.
庞贝的子民
People of Pompeii!
火神说话了
Vulcan speaks!
火神裁定那个人是庞贝的冠军
Vulcan decrees that man to
be the champion of Pompeii!
他值得挺身当面对抗罗马强权
Decrees that he is worthy to stand
face-to-face against
the might of Rome!
伟大的火神
Great Vulcan, we hear you
speak and will obey!
我们听到您说话并会遵循
普罗克路斯
Proculus...
让这些懦夫见识
Show these cowards
what really happens
胆敢挑战罗马强权的下场
when you dare to challenge
the might of Rome.
乐意之至
With pleasure.
快点
Come on! Come on!
快走
Faster! Move it!
怎么回事？小姐？
What's going on? My Lady?
别碰她，放开她
Don't touch her! Let her go!
凯西雅
Cassia!
由昆塔亚兹科佛斯议员主持
By the patronage of Senator
Quintas Attius Corvus,
罗马的冠军
the champion of Rome,
马克斯普罗克路斯
Marcus Proculus, hero of
the Celtic Rebellion,
歼灭凯尔特人的英雄
现在会面对庞贝的新冠军
will now face the new champion
of Pompeii, The Celt,
凯尔特
展开单挑
in single combat!
提图斯皇帝万岁
All hail to Emperor Titus!
我知道你
I know you.
真的？
Really?
无论你想报什么仇
Well, whatever revenge you
think you're going to have,
恐怕你会失望
I'm afraid you'll be disappointed.
给这奴隶像样的剑
Bring this slave a better sword.
刀刃是钝的
This blade's dull.
是吗？
Is it?
给大家看一场好戏吧
Let's give them a good show, huh?
杀了他！
Kill him!
快杀了他！
Kill him now!
不！
No!
你很勇敢，我很佩服
You're brave. I'll give you that.
但野蛮人绝对敌不过罗马人
But no savage could ever
be the match for a Roman.
那我们20人呢？
How about 20 of us?
不要！
No!
等等，等等
Wait! Wait!
不要！
No!
怜悯我！
Mercy!
不要！不要！
No!
很高兴见到你，兄弟
Good to see you, brother.
我也是
And you.
欧蕾莉亚
Aurelia.
杀了他
Kill him.
经过再三考虑
On further consideration,
我决定不投资你的小城市
I have decided not to
invest in your little city.
送我到港口
Get me to the harbor.
对不起
I'm sorry.
让开
Move. Move it!
你！
You! Come here!
过来这里
我的船费
For my passage.
让他上船
Let him aboard.
你们要赶快离开
You must leave now!
起锚，准备启航
Cast off! Prepare to set sail!
救命
Help me! Please!
你...
You...
你一定要帮助我们
You have to help us.
你一定要解救凯西雅
You have to save Cassia.
她在哪里？
Where is she?
别墅
The villa.
你要去哪里？
- Where are you going?
- I have to find her.
我要去找她
米洛，别异想天开了
Milo, this is madness!
我们要去港口，找艘船
We have to get to the
harbor and find a boat.
火山会烧死所有人
The mountain is going
to kill us all!
她为了我冒生命危险，阿提卡斯
She risked her life
for me, Atticus.
为了我不顾一切
Risked everything for me!
没有她，我们早就死在竞技场
Without her, they would have
killed us in that arena!
那我们一起去
Then we will go together.
不行
No.
你获得你的自由，我的朋友
You have your freedom, my friend.
现在她是我的目标
Now she is mine.
那我们在港口碰面
Then we meet at the harbor.
港口见
At the harbor.
拜托，给我钥匙
Please, give me the keys!
凯西雅，他们拿走钥匙
Cassia, they've taken the keys!
No!
她在哪里？
Where is she?
拿水来
Water!
你为了我回来
You came back for me.
喝吧
Drink. Drink.
谢谢，姊妹
Thank you, sister.
不要！
No!
看着我
Look at me.
我们要赶去港口
We have to get to the harbor.
这样是自杀，回头
This is suicide. Turn around! Back!
回去
让路
Out of the way!
Get out of the way!
够了
Enough!
杀了他们，杀光他们
Kill them! Kill them all!
快划，白痴，快划
Row, you idiots! Row!
回头，你们得回头
Turn around! You have to turn back!
起来，起来
Come on. Get up! Get up!
不！
No! No, my daughter!
不！不！
Getup!
No!
我的女儿
My daughter!
妈咪
Mommy! Help!
这是世界末日吗？
Is this the end of the world?
为何神会让这种事发生？
Why would the gods let this happen?
米洛
- Milo!
- Atticus!
阿提卡斯
我知道诸神绝对抓不到你
I knew the gods would
never catch you.
你太快了，现在我懂原因了
There's none faster.
And now I see why.
该走了，我的朋友- 不行
- It's time to go, my friend...
- No.
港口不见了，我们得另找出路
The harbor's gone. We
have to find another way.
那我们往南进入丘陵
Then we have to go
south into the hills.
太远了，我们走路到不了
It's too far. We'll
never make it on foot.
那我们去那里
Then we go there.
竞技场？为什么？
The arena? Why?
有马
Horses.
我的父母亲
My parents.
我去牵马
I'll get the horses.
别去
Don't.
去帮你朋友
Go help your friend.
阿提卡斯？
Atticus?
到处是罗马人
Romans everywhere.
走吧
Let's go.
你最好舒服待着
You better get
comfortable, my dear.
到罗马还很远
It's a long way to Rome.
你为何这样做？
Why are you doing this?
因为凡是我的资产
Because the property of
Quintas Attius Corvus
不准被随便个奴隶抢去
will not be taken by some slave.
普罗克路斯，没你位子了
Proculus, there's not
enough room for you.
那我们罗马见，议员
Then I shall see you
in Rome, Senator.
科佛斯！
Corvus!
我悬赏一千取那奴隶的人头
1,000 dinari to the man who
brings me the head of that slave!
Hyah! Hyah!
现在换我了，快去
This is mine now. Go.
阿提卡斯
Atticus...
再不去就追不回她了
Every second takes her
further away from you.
后会有期，兄弟
I'll see you again, brother.
Hyah! Hyah!
Hyah!
Go on!
野蛮人死不足惜，不像罗马人
A barbarian does not die
the equal of a Roman.
胡扯
Equal!
求求你
来瞧瞧罗马人
Let's see if a Roman
跟斗士决一死战的结果
can die the equal of a gladiator.
不要
No!
求求你
Please. Please.
斗士不会乞求
Gladiators do not beg.
Hyah!
贱人，你这贱人
Bitch! You bitch!
等等
Wait! Wait! Wait!
等等，等等
你跟我有何深仇大恨？
Who are you to do this to me?
我是昆塔亚兹科佛斯议员
I am Senator Quintas Attius Corvus!
那又怎样？昆塔亚兹科佛斯议员
And what is that worth,
Senator Quintas Attius Corvus?
你残杀我家人，屠杀我族人
You killed my family,
you slaughtered my people,
and make no mistake,
无庸置疑
我的神找上你了
my gods are coming for you.
等等
Wait!
你不能把我留在这里
You can't leave me here!
赴死的同袍
For those of us about to die...
我们向你们致敬
We salute you!
我以自由之身死去
I die a free man!
你快把马骑走
You have to ride him out of here.
不要
- No!
- He's not fast enough.
它不够快
载不了我们两人，快走
He can't carry us both! Go!
不要，我不会丢下你
No, I won't leave you!
你别无选择
We don't have a choice.
快跑，快走
Run! Go!
我不愿浪费最后相聚的一刻逃命
I don't want to spend our
last moments running.
别看
Don't look.
看着我
Look at me.
只要看着我